Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast
with the latest peer-
reviewed research
on the best ways to eat
healthy and live longer.
Today we ask, why doesn’t
everyone just eat healthier?
Right? It seems like
such a simple solution
to so many of our problems.
As it turns out, the
answer is complicated.
Here’s our first story.
Yes, media messages surrounding
nutrition are often
inconsistent and confusing,
but many Americans know
what constitutes a healthy diet.
I mean, does anyone
really think drinking brown
carbonated sugar water
is good for them?
At issue is that they don’t appear to be
translating their knowledge into action.
There are a number of reasons
people have such difficulty
changing their dietary behaviors.
While ignorance and
confusion may play a part,
the motivation to change is
likely much more important.
Certainly, we are living in
a world that pushes us to eat
whatever we want, regardless of
the long-term consequences.
But one of the major problems in
getting people to change their
behavior is the need to get them
to recognize the need to change.
For example, if you ask
people how much meat they eat,
or how much greasy food, eggs,
sweets, alcohol, butter,
they claim to be eating less
than the average person.
So, if people think they’re
at less risk than others,
they may dismiss advice
to eat more healthfully,
thinking that they already eat
healthier. Maybe they are?
No, people rated their own
eating behavior as healthier
on average even when their actual
eating habits were terrible.
For this reason, maybe health-
promotion campaigns need to make
people aware of how
badly they are eating.
But when you do that,
a strange thing happens.
If you challenge people with
the reality of what the average
person actually eats, they
change their answer to make
themselves appear as though they’re
still healthier than average.
When people's favorable
comparisons on risky behaviors
are threatened, they not
only reduce their estimates
of how often they engage
in those behaviors—
"oh, I don’t eat that much meat”—
but they also attenuate the
significance of those behaviors.
“Meat’s not that bad for you anyway.”
It’s the same personal fable
that smokers tell themselves.
Studies show that smokers
have a strong tendency
to underestimate all
smoking-related risks,
developing a series of
illusions and false beliefs
to support their choice
to keep on smoking.
Why do so many people continue
to light up in spite of
smoking’s harmful
effects to their health?
For many of the same reasons people
continue to eat unhealthy food.
First, they convince
themselves that they are less
at risk than others who
engage in the same behavior.
And in addition to this optimism
bias, smokers underestimate
the extent to which smoking
elevates lung cancer risk,
thinking two-pack-a-day smokers
only have like five times the risk
of getting lung cancer, when their
actual risk is 20-fold higher.
And anyway, many
smokers believe lung cancer
is mainly determined by one’s genes.
Many food-related hazards
share this same optimistic bias,
such as heart attacks and
heart disease (our #1 killer),
obesity, diabetes, and all the rest.
People are often quite
ingenious in finding reasons for
believing that their own risk is less
than the risk faced by their peers.
So, maybe public health advocates
need to be just as ingenious
in understanding the origins
of this unrealistic optimism
and in finding approaches
that help people gain a more
accurate picture of
their own vulnerability.
All sorts of work is being done
trying to reduce or eliminate
this bias, “but we must
consider the possibility that
reductions in optimistic
bias may lead to reductions
in self-esteem and
psychological well-being,”
if people start to realize
just how much risk they
truly face and how much they
have themselves to blame.
This reminds me of the tightrope
wire health professionals
have to walk, telling
people how much power
we all have over getting cancer.
This is the oft-cited paper
that calculated that we may
be able to prevent approximately
90 percent of human cancers.
(But by “present trends,” the
researcher was talking about
present trends of the 1960s
when the paper was published.)
They remain true to this day, though,
about a half century later.
Genetic factors are not the
major causes of chronic diseases.
Using identical twins to see
how much was really just
in your genes, of all the chronic
diseases they looked at,
cancers had the lowest
genetic component,
again only about 10 percent
attributable to bad genes.
What runs in families is bad habits.
But when you go out there and
tell everyone the good news
about how much power we
have over not getting cancer,
what about the people
who already have it?
When people are diagnosed
with cancer, they often ask,
“Why me? Did I do something
wrong? Is this my fault?”
So you can imagine how the
message of, “well yeah, kinda,”
could be destructive for
patients or survivors.
In other words, a message that
is intended to empower people in
a prevention context could just
make cancer victims feel guilty.
But the truth is still the truth,
no matter how difficult it may be.
So, what we have to do is
try to guide patients to switch
from feelings of guilt to a
“responsibility” approach.
They have personal control;
they can make different
choices from then on.
We need to give them a sense
of agency in their life.
Better, though, to try to take
those steps before you get cancer.
In our next story, we look at how
most deaths in the United States
are preventable and
related to nutrition.
Does it really matter what we eat?
Well, the good news is,
we have tremendous power
over our health destiny and longevity—
the majority of premature death
and disability is preventable
with a healthy enough diet.
It's. . . the. . . food.
Most deaths in the United States
are preventable and related to nutrition.
According to the most rigorous analysis
of risk factors ever published,
The Global Burden of Disease Study,
funded by the Bill & Melinda
Gates Foundation,
the number one cause
of death in the United States,
and the number one
cause of disability,
is our diet, which has bumped
tobacco smoking to #2.
Smoking now only kills about a
half million Americans every year,
whereas our diet kills hundreds
of thousands more.
What we eat is the #1
determinant of how long we live.
What we eat is what determines
most whether we'll die prematurely.
What we eat is what determines most
whether we become disabled or not.
So, if our diet is the #1 cause
of death and disability,
if most deaths in the United States
are preventable and related to nutrition,
then obviously nutrition is the #1
thing taught in medical school, right?
Obviously it's the #1 thing your doctor
talks to you about at every visit, right?
Unfortunately, doctors suffer from
a severe nutrition deficiency —
in education.
Most doctors are just never taught
about the impact healthy nutrition
can have on the course of illness,
and so they graduate without this
powerful tool in their medical toolbox.
Now, there are also
institutional barriers,
such as time constraints
and lack of reimbursement.
In general, doctors aren't
paid for counseling people
on how to take better
care of themselves.
Of course, the drug
companies also play a role
in influencing medical
education and practice.
Ask your doctor
when's the last time
they were taken out to
dinner by Big Broccoli;
it's probably been awhile.
That's why I started
NutritionFacts.org.
It's the tool I wish I had
in medical training.
NutritionFacts.org is a free, nonprofit,
science-based public service,
providing daily updates on the latest
in nutrition research via bite-sized videos.
There are videos on more than 2,000
health and nutrition topics—all free—
with new videos and articles
uploaded every day
on the latest in
evidence-based nutrition.
What a concept.
Finally today,
we know for a fact
that a healthy plant-based diet
could help reverse the
#1 killer of men and women.
So shouldn’t that
be the default diet,
until proven otherwise?
There is only one diet that's ever
been proven to reverse heart disease
in the majority of patients: a diet
centered around whole plant foods.
So anytime anyone tries to sell
you on some new diet,
do me a favor; ask them
one simple question:
"Has it been proven to
reverse heart disease?"
You know, the number one reason
you and all your loved ones will die.
If the answer is, "No," why
would you even consider it?
Only one diet has ever
been proven to do that.
That's not cherry picking;
there's only one cherry.
In fact, if that's all a plant-
based diet could do—
reverse the #1 killer
of men and women—
shouldn't that be the default
diet until proven otherwise?
And the fact that it can also be effective
in preventing, arresting, and reversing
other leading killers like
type 2 diabetes, and hypertension
would seem to make the case for
plant-based eating simply overwhelming.
So why don't more
doctors prescribe it?
How could there be such
a disconnect between the science
and mainstream medical practice?
Well look, it took 25 years
before the first Surgeon General's
report against smoking came out.
It took more than 7,000 studies, and
the deaths of countless smokers,
before the powers-that-be
officially recognized the link.
(You'd think that after
the first 6,000 studies
they could have given people
a little heads up or something?)
Powerful industry, right?
In fact, even after the Surgeon
General's report came out,
the medical community
still dragged their feet.
The American Medical Association
actually went on record
refusing to endorse the
Surgeon General's report. Why?
Could it have been because
they had just been handed
a 10 million dollar check from
the tobacco industry?
Maybe. . .
So we know why the AMA may have
been sucking up to the tobacco industry,
but why weren't individual
doctors speaking out?
There were a few gallant souls ahead
of their time writing in, as there are today,
standing up against industries
killing millions, but why not more?
Maybe it's because the majority of
physicians themselves smoked cigarettes,
just like the majority of physicians
today continue to eat foods
that are contributing to our
epidemics of dietary disease.
What was the AMA's
rallying cry back then?
"Everything in moderation.
"Extensive scientific studies have
proven that smoking in moderation...
"Oh, that's fine."
Sound familiar?
Consumption of animal foods
and processed foods may cause
at least 14 million deaths
around the world every year.
14 million people dead.
Those of us involved in this evidence-
based nutrition revolution are part
of a movement with 14 million
lives in the balance every year.
Plant-based diets may
now be considered
the nutritional equivalent
of quitting smoking.
How many more people have
to die though before the CDC
encourages people not to wait for open-heart
surgery to start eating healthy as well?
Until the system changes, we have
to take personal responsibility for our
own health, for our family's health.
We can't wait until society catches
up to the science again,
because it's a matter
of life and death.
Last year, Dr. Kim Williams became President
of the American College of Cardiology.
He was asked in an interview
why he follows his own advice
to eat a plant-based diet?
"I don't mind dying," Dr. Williams replied,
"I just don't want it to be my own fault."
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.